Okay, let's get started for today.
Let's start with a recap of what we
covered last time because we're going to
be building very heavily on uh
Wednesday's concepts. So we talked about
online reinforcement learning where we
collect a batch of data with some policy
by running that policy in the
environment and then we try to use that
data to improve our policy and then we
repeat this process uh in order to get
uh kind of continue to improve from
practice.
Uh we talked about an online
reinforcement learning algorithm called
policy gradients. uh and the update for
our policy looks something like this
where we first take samples from our
policy. This will give us n different
trajectories sampled from our policy. Um
we will evaluate the log likelihood of
the policy. And so this pi here is
representing a distribution over actions
given states. And so this is looking
like the gradient of the log probability
of the actions uh under the policy. And
this log likelihood is weighted by the
reward that the agent got. And so if you
have higher rewards uh as an outcome of
your actions in the future, then you're
going to be encouraging the policy to
increase the likelihood of those
actions. And then lastly, we introduced
a baseline which was a uh which we could
define to be the average reward such
that we're increasing the likelihood on
futures that were above average reward
and decreasing the likelihood on futures
that on actions that led to futures that
were below average reward.
Um so you can think of this sort of as
doing encouraging the policy to do more
of the above average stuff less of the
below average stuff and then repeating
that process uh to get better and
better.
Cool. Um we also talked about how this
algorithm is fully on policy. Uh so we
need to uh in order to evaluate this we
actually need to have samples from pi
theta from our current policy. And this
meant that we could only take one
gradient step per batch of data. Uh
which is disappointing because then we'd
have to take collect a ton and ton of
data in order to improve. Uh this kind
of brings up this notion of having on
policy versus off policy algorithms that
can reuse data from other past policies.
And we started to look at ways to make
an algorithm off policy. Uh and in
particular we talked about using
importance weights. uh where if we
weight the objective by the probability
of the actions of the new policy divided
by the probability of the actions under
the old policy. This is a way to get a
estimate of uh the gradient for the new
policy.
Um I should also mention that importance
weights uh the math behind it uh is is
very simple and very nice. Uh but it's
important to remember that this isn't a
silver bullet. uh this sort of approach
is only suitable when the policies are
very similar to one another and if the
policies are very different then this
ratio uh will get very large or very
small uh and you'll also just have a
worse estimate of your gradient.
Okay. Um so today we're going to be
talking about a form of algorithms
called actor critic methods that build
on policy gradients. And um we'll talk
about as part of this we'll be talking
about how to estimate the value of a
policy. Um and then we'll introduce an
off policy variant of of the algorithm.
Um and these actor methods are uh the
basis for algorithms like PO uh which
are used to train language models and
that are used to train um uh like
humanoids and simulation uh and so
forth.
So very very useful uh RL algorithms. Uh
and then the key learning goals for
today is how to estimate how good a
state and action is for a policy. Uh
this is called policy evaluation. Uh
it's very a critical aspect of actor
critic methods but also useful more
broadly and then also talk about how to
use those estimates to form a better
reinforcement learning algorithm.
Cool. Um
so let's get started. uh and to talk
about these algorithms, we need to
revisit some very useful objects that we
talked about uh in the first lecture and
specifically this is value functions. Um
and so a value function is representing
how good a a state is uh if you're going
to follow a policy starting from that
state. And you can think of it as uh the
sum of rewards
starting from used to writing gradients
uh starting from some state. So we'll
write this as um v pi of s this means
that we're going to be starting at state
s and then running pi. And uh for a
given state, this is equal to the sum of
rewards if we were to
start at
uh state t and go to the end of the
trajectory and here's the sum of
rewards. Now, um, this sum of rewards is
going to, uh, differ depending on what
state we start at and depending on what
policy that we're running. And so, this
is going to be, um, an expectation
uh, of
um, under our policy. Actually, maybe
it's easier to write this um, as
expectation on the inside. So this is an
expectation over uh the states ST prime
um and actions Aprime that will be
visited uh under our policy uh and
conditioned on the fact that we're
starting at state ST.
Um so we can think about uh the value
function as this. uh just in terms of
math what you can think about this as is
or just in terms of like conceptually or
in in terms of intuition if you have
some trajectory uh and you're thinking
about the value of this state you can
think of it as if we were to collect a
lot of different trajectories starting
from that state from our policy
uh and then we just summed up the
rewards uh from this time step to the
end and then averaged over these
trajectories that would define the value
of the state or how good the state is
for the policy. Another useful quantity
uh that we'll be making use of is called
the Q function. And this is a slightly
different from the value function but
very closely related. Uh and the
difference is that instead of um just
thinking about the value of a given
state, we're going to be thinking about
a value of a given state and action. Uh
and what this is referring to is uh if
you were to instead of starting at S and
then running pi from there, if instead
we were to start at S, take a particular
action A and then run the policy, what
is our expected sum of rewards?
Um and so then you can think of this as
uh instead of uh if a picture like this
um say we had some state s that we
considered and first we're going to take
some given action. This may or may not
have been what the policy would have
been likely to choose.
Uh this action could actually also lead
to different states if the uh because
the uh the environment is stoastic and
then it's
the sum of
these rewards uh on average. Um so this
is what uh V looks like. This is what Q
looks like for a given action.
Um so here are some pictures on the
slide. So if we take start from state s
run our policy we compute the expected
sum of the rewards along these
trajectories then that gets us the value
of a state and then if instead we take
action a first and then run pi then we
get the key values and it's just the sum
of the rewards um if we had started with
action A.
Now one last uh one thing that's useful
to think about in terms of how these two
relate to each other is you can think of
the value of a state as um if you take
an expectation over the actions that the
policy would have taken. Uh you can
think of it as um the average or the
expectation of the Q values over all the
actions that the policy would have
taken.
Um and then one last object object that
we'll use today um is thinking about how
good is a particular action relative to
other actions that we might take.
Uh and for this we can think about like
what is if you um if you consider uh the
Q value minus the value function that's
going to tell you like how good is it to
take action A versus following the
policy at a given state and this is kind
of like what is the advantage of um of
taking one action versus following the
policy.
Great question. So the question was is
there a normalization
um
between V and Q? Um the you can think of
an expectation as an average. Uh and so
in that sense uh there is going to be a
normalization. Um because if you if you
were to like for example try to estimate
this expectation with samples um you
would take um some number of samples. If
you only use these two samples to
estimate Q, then you would divide by two
versus here, if you're using five
samples, you would divide by five. Um,
is there a way that you can get from
this equation to the useful relation on
the slide? Is that what you're asking?
Um,
yeah. So, the if you write out um
the
so if you write out we can write out
first what qi looks like. So um
qi of a given state and action we're
going to uh assume that we we're going
to condition on st a t uh because that's
where we're starting and then this is
the expected sum of rewards if we um
so a sum over t prime equals t to t um
and then we're going to have an
expectation of running the policy
um
here and then uh a sum of rewards
and then in terms of seeing um the like
how to get between these two things. Uh
this is a um you can think of this as a
sum of rewards of um under uh a sampled
from or kind of future actions sampled
from pi. Uh whereas this one a is not
sampled but from pi but all future
actions are sampled from pi. In this
case we're uh kind of conditioning on um
on the action that's kind of provided as
input. In this case we're sampling from
the policy. And so if instead uh you
sample the um the action from the policy
and then feed that in to here uh then
you'll get the um then you'll get this
right here.
Okay. So to help you start thinking
about some of these quantities uh let's
look at an example. Uh and so say that
you are um this person right here. Uh
you really want to learn how to play the
drums. uh and your reward is one if you
can play the music in a month and zero
otherwise. So capital T is a month from
now. And your action space uh you have
three different possible actions in your
action space. Uh one action is to like
sit on the beach. Another action is to
uh watch TV and another action is to
practice playing the drums.
uh and say that your current policy uh
right now is just to sit on the beach uh
and you do that for all states.
Now my question for you to think about
uh is what are each of these quantities
uh for the action of A1, for the action
of A2 and for the action of A3. And so
specifically you want to think about
what is the uh what is the value
function of your current state for this
policy.
uh what is your Q function for um if you
were to follow each of these actions and
uh once and then follow this policy uh
and then what is your advantage function
um for uh for the current state that
you're in um and for each of these
actions and you can assume that uh in
the current state that you're in you do
not know how to play the drums. What was
described is for the value function uh
for this particular policy that's always
sitting on the beach the value is zero
uh because it the the person would not
learn to play the drum. So that's the
sum of expected rewards for this policy
for vi uh for the q function uh if you
uh sit on the beach at the current time
step or or watch TV uh the q function
will be zero for those actions. Uh
whereas for if if the the Q function for
playing the drums at the current time
step um would be one if if that amount
of practicing um is sufficient. It's
also possible that it would be a bit
lower than one if you for example
practice for like um like an hour and
then sit on the beach by following the
policy afterwards. It kind of depends a
little bit on what the time kind of how
long a given time step is. Uh and then
the advantage function is um is going to
be Q minus V. And so it's going to be a
positive number for the action of
practicing and it'll be zero for the
other two actions. Yeah. So the question
is um if practicing is like not enough
to actually learn would it would it be
one would it be between zero and one
would it be zero? Um it basically
actually represents the probability in
which you would be able to play this
given that you had practiced for that
amount of time. And that probability um
uh it could be zero like maybe this is
like really really hard after just
practicing once. Um uh it it could also
be like maybe for someone who's like
extremely talented they only need to
practice once. Um and so that could be a
bit higher for someone that's like a bit
more talented. Um it it depends on
various stackers like that. Yeah. um
kind of along those lines, if you think
about the value function um for like if
you're playing like a a game of chess
for example, uh the value function is
the probability that um you're going to
win for um for a given person and for a
given game state. So it's kind of
evaluating um how good is the state for
a particular person. That's another way
to think about it.
Okay, cool. So um those are the objects
that we're going to be using quite a bit
today. Now let's go back to policy
gradients and see how we can use value
functions to make this algorithm better.
Uh so we talked about a couple examples
on Wednesday of of some satis some some
scenarios that were dissatisfying about
policy gradients. Um and the first was
that if we are trying to learn how to
walk and we have a policy that takes a
small step forwards and then falls
backwards uh we will push down the
likelihood of taking a step forwards uh
because we don't necessarily know that
might have led it to fall backwards. Um
now if we actually had some
understanding that taking a small step
forward was making progress was actually
good was advantageous then um we might
be able to actually increase the
likelihood of that. Um and so this is
starting to hint at some of the
intuition behind actor critic methods.
Um and likewise we talked about this uh
example of trying to fold a jacket and
we found that um if you have a sparse
reward uh where uh and you only do part
of the task like folding only the
sleeves or or flattening the jacket but
not folding it um you aren't really
utilizing uh the trajectories that are
getting zero reward. uh and
kind of similar to this case, if we
instead kind of understood that these
actions are advantageous for making
progress on the task, then we might
actually be able to figure out how to
use these trajectories in a positive
way. And so kind of to summarize here,
policy gradients don't always make an
efficient use of data that we've
collected. And if we can try to figure
out what actions are advantageous versus
not advantageous, we might be able to
make better use of that data. So the
question was if it's not clear if a
positive step if a step forward is is um
is helpful or not is that going to be
negative or neutral. Um in the case of
the policy gradient uh in case of this
policy gradient algorithm um this the
trajectory that we considered here in
the context of the batch of directories
was kind of net negative was below
average because the reward to go is
quite negative. it's actually making
backwards progress uh in the um in this
trajectory and so it actually is going
to be pushing down the likelihood of
taking a step forward uh because the
future reward to go is negative. Um and
what we'll talk about today is uh
algorithms that in principle could
actually increase the likelihood for
taking the step forward and decrease the
likelihood for falling backwards.
Okay. Um, so how do we do that? Uh, a
lot of what we'll focus on today is this
piece right here. This is what's
actually telling us that we should push
down the likelihood if we have negative
rewards in the future.
Um, and this quantity, it's estimating
the future rewards uh if we take action
A in state S. And so we can kind of
think about it as uh in this picture
right here. Uh it looks a lot like uh
what is the sum of rewards um if we
started right here with uh state S and
action A. And then if we think about
this picture uh
we were looking at this quantity in
terms of like what we observed in
trajectories. Uh but what would be an
even better version of this quantity
would be to actually use the Q function.
uh and if we could replace this with the
Q function uh then we would be able to
get a much better um estimate of whether
or not we should push up the likelihood
or push down the likelihood. And so
looking at the slides right now what we
do is we for like a single trajectory we
sum together the rewards that we saw
which was in the in the case the example
before um the rewards were negative
because we took a small step forwards
and then fell backwards. Um but if
instead what we could do is actually run
the policy many many times and get a Q
function for the state
that would be the true expected rewards
to go under the expectation of our
policy and this would be way better. Uh
we'd be able to get a much better sense
for how good um how good it was to take
that action in that state.
Um so
essentially the form of the gradient
would um it would be a be able to get a
much better gradient if the form of the
gradient looked like this where we
increase the likelihood of the actions
for things that have high Q values and
we decrease the likelihood of the
actions for things that have low Q
values.
So that's kind of a first step. Um
now taking things one step further uh we
also talked about baselines in the
previous lecture where the baseline was
the average reward. Um should we use a
baseline here?
So uh before the baselines were the
average reward. Uh and so in this case
if we were to introduce baselines we
could think about what we might use. Um,
and
if we use the same thing that we used
before, we could use like the average Q
value in this case. Um, so we could use
uh an average
like maybe we sample some uh some S SI
and AI and we average over those.
uh and
what we had talked about a few slides
ago is actually um this is actually
looking a lot like the value function.
And so we we talked about uh the value
of a given state is an expectation over
um actions sampled from the policy for
that given state
of the Q function
for those actions. This is V pi. And so
a natural baseline would actually be to
use the value function. Uh and so
we could have instead of having this be
Q values, we could actually use Q minus
V. Uh, and Q minus V is what the
advantage function is.
Uh, and so putting this together, we
would be increasing the likelihood
for actions that have a high advantage
and decreasing the likelihood for
actions that have a low advantage. And
so then if you think back to uh the
example of learning to practice playing
the drums, uh we would be increasing the
the action of practicing had a high
advantage relative to the current
policy. And so then we would choose to
increase the likelihood for practicing
and decrease the likelihood for the
other act for the other actions.
Cool. Um and another way to think about
this is that better estimates of this
advantage function will lead to less
noisy gradient. Uh and if we knew the
true advantage function then we would be
able to get uh a very very good
gradient. Um unfortunately we don't know
the true advantage function. And so uh
the next question uh that we'll talk
about over the next several slides is
how can we estimate the advantage
function? Right? So the question was um
like like how is this different
different from like how we're sampling
um in the original policy gradient and
so what we're using before is we were
doing this like we would take kind of
one sample um and then for like a given
state and action uh in that uh
trajectory we would sum the rewards just
for that individual thing. Uh and now
what we're saying is that instead of and
this is going to be like a very noisy
estimate because we just have one
trajectory here. We just have one data
point to estimate these rewards. Um and
now what we're saying here is that we're
going to try to get a sense for what the
advantage of this action is. Now
one way we'll actually start to talk
about how we do that uh in a minute. Um
but if you if you want to think about
what is the true advantage of this
action conceptually if you were to um
take this uh state and action and then
roll out the policy an infinite number
of times uh for this action versus for
following the policy in other scenarios
that that's what would give us the
advantage. Yeah. So the question is um
in policy gradient we were we got to
where we were by optimizing the expected
sum of rewards. um does this also
optimize some objective. Uh so this is
also optimizing the expected sum of
rewards and it's actually optimizing the
same exact function. Um the
uh we haven't talked about how to get a
yet, but if you had a perfect A, um this
would also like this would be giving you
the correct gradient for that objective.
um modulo kind of the the sampling here
being used uh to sample states and
actions. Is the baseline an average over
the current trajectory or an average
over all trajectories? Yeah. Um the for
the uh so if we set it to be the Q
function the the the value function V um
that would be like an infinite number of
samples. Um we haven't yet talked about
how we're actually going to estimate A.
Um or estimate Q versus V. Uh so we'll
talk about that in a minute. Uh but
yeah, for V like if you the conceptually
that would be like over an infinite
number, but I'm talking about like the
this is the true value so far. Uh we
haven't talked about how to estimate the
the value yet. Yeah. So the question is
is this unbiased? Um it is unbiased. Uh
you can go through the math. I won't go
through that today uh for the sake of
time. Uh but yeah, this is an unbiased
estimate of the gradient if you have the
true advantage. Um now we will see
things that are biased later today.
Okay, so let's actually talk about how
do we um how do we use this um and
actually just as a as a quick overview
of what the algorithm will look like for
this form of algorithm. Um before we had
this loop between running the policy and
improving the policy. Now, we're going
to have an additional step where we're
going to fit a model that's going to
estimate the expected return. And
essentially, it's going to try to
estimate uh this a right here.
Um and so our our new algorithm will
have a few different steps. One is to
run the policy, one is to try to
estimate um estimate values, uh and then
the last will be then to use that
estimate um and the data that was
collected to improve the policy.
Um and so this step will involve
estimating either v pi, qi or a pi. And
um this step will be uh kind of similar
to before except it's going to use uh
these estimates right here.
Okay. So um let's get to how do we
actually estimate uh these values? Uh so
we we want to estimate this uh this
quantity right here. And
to start out, um, we need to think about
how we want to get to a pi.
And we could try to directly fit a pi,
although it's actually a little bit
challenging to get direct supervision
for the advantages.
Uh, and so we're actually going to try
to uh fit vpi. The way that we're going
to get there um is
we let's see where do we want to go? Um
we know that uh a pi
of st a t
is equal to the
q value
minus the value.
And so,
um, one option is we could try to
estimate these two, although then we'd
still have to estimate two objects. Uh,
and there's actually a way to turn this
into an equation that actually only
depends on V pi. And that would be nice
because then we could just only fit V pi
and then derive a pi from there to get
the gradient.
Uh and so to do this um we can think
about uh qi right here. And
this q function um this is the the value
of starting in s taking a and then
summing the rewards. And so you can
think of it as the
reward at
the current time step that you got plus
the rewards that would come after that.
And in terms of the rewards that would
come after that, you'll have some next
state s+ one. Uh and so you can think of
it as um
there's some next state you don't um
there's actually some uh this next state
could be a few different things
depending on your environment. So this
would be sampled from
the dynamics of the environment.
And
then um after this state, it's
essentially going to be the sum of
rewards starting at ST+1 and following
your policy.
And the sum of rewards starting at uh
sorry, this should be ST+1. The sum of
rewards starting at ST+1.
Uh that's equal to the value, right? The
value of ST+1. Uh so we can
write the
um this Q value as the reward at the
current time step plus the value at the
time step after that.
Now we can't sample from these dynamics.
Uh but when we ran our policy to collect
data we did actually see one outcome one
ST plus one. And so we can approximate
this as the reward at the current time
step plus the value at the next time
step.
And then if we want to estimate the
advantage, we can write it as the reward
at the current time step plus the value
at the next time step minus the value at
the current time step.
And so
maybe I'll do this in a different color
to differentiate it. So now a pi can be
written as
of st
can be approximated as r the reward that
you saw plus the value at the next time
step minus the value at the current time
step.
And so if we then have an estimate of V
for our policy
then we can estimate the advantage and
we can just try to directly fit V.
And so on the slides what this looks
like we have Q. Q can be written as the
expected future rewards. Um and uh which
is the reward at the current time step
plus the future rewards. These future
rewards are can be written as the value.
And so we can think of Q as the reward
at the current time step plus the value
at the next time step. Um
yeah. So why is um why is the second to
last line why is this an approximation?
Um the the reason for this is that the
next state uh there's actually multiple
possible next states. Uh, and we're just
going to use one sample from this
expectation, which is the sample that we
saw when we rolled out the trajectory in
our data. Um, and if if you wanted an
exact thing, you would need to estimate
this expectation with like infinite
samples. How good of an approximation is
this? So, um, it is going to be a single
sample approximation. Uh, the the good
news is that later on we'll see ways to
use lots of data to do this. Um uh and
so it's in general well so I guess the
first thing is if you're if this is very
deterministic it's going to be first
it's going to be a good estimate because
there aren't that many futures um if
it's more stoastic then it's going to be
a worse estimate and then we'll see ways
in which we can use uh data and take
lots of gradient steps uh in a way that
makes it not too bad so the question is
is there any new uh interaction with the
environment so um I guess we haven't yet
talked about how to fit vpi Okay. Uh so
we will talk about that uh in the next
slide. Yeah. So you'll have some if you
have some trajectory uh the this will be
like the st and s+ one in your
trajectory from the same trajectory.
Yeah. So you need to use the same
trajectory for this. Uh and I sometimes
I forget to put the pi on here. Um and
there is a lot of reinforcement learning
work that drops the pies just for
simplicity. But it is actually in some
ways very important to have a pi there
because it is estimating a value for a
particular policy uh not for any policy.
Uh so the question is why are we
choosing to estimate V versus Q versus
A? Um it's just a little bit simpler uh
in practice. Uh but you can also uh
there are also ways to directly estimate
Q. Um and actually we'll talk about some
of those ways uh next week as well.
Okay. Cool.
Um, so we're just going to fit VPI and
then once we fit VI, we can get the
advantage and then plug that into our
gradient for our policy.
Uh, we'll we can represent VPI as a
neural network and what this will look
like is we'll pass as input a state and
then um it will output a single scalar
value uh not as pictured here a single
scalar value that represents the value
of that state for that policy. Um this
neural network will have some
parameters.
Um so how do we do this? Uh so there's a
few different ways to estimate EP pi. Um
the first version um
so in the very very initial version like
of of vanilla policy gradients we just
used a single trajectory a single sample
um and we kind of instead of actually
learning a model we just use that
sample. Um
in principle we could also
use many samples and then uh and then
yeah use many samples. Unfortunately if
you were to try to go to a particular
state and then take many samples from
that state that means that you would
have to be able to kind of reset the
world to that state and uh kind of see
what happens if you took many different
rollouts from that same state. Uh and
unfortunately in many scenarios it's
very hard to reset the state. Um if you
are in kind of simulated settings uh
sometimes you can actually reset the
simulator. Uh so there is sometimes
scenarios where you can do this but in
practice uh we typically don't do this.
Um so since we can't like kind of
directly reset and take lots of samples
uh what we can do is we can use multiple
trajectories that we had sampled and
just train a single model on the
original single sample estimate and
because our kind of the trajectories
that we have they will have um some
states in them that are similar you'll
be able to um
essentially learn how to uh kind of like
amortize uh the the data. So you'll see
you'll see some examples in the
environment that have very similar
states and have uh kind of corresponding
future rewards in them. And with that
repetition in your data, a neural
network can actually learn um kind of
have a little bit more density in terms
of uh this the rewards that you'll see
for a given state.
And so what this is going to look like
is you can take your data set and
for all of the
um you'll have like
uh i= 1 to n trajectories and each
trajectory will have time steps in it
and for all of those uh
uh trajectories and time steps you'll
also have some sum of rewards that you
observe for that. Uh so you'll have some
sum of rewards that started at t uh to
the end of the
rewards of the uh of the states uh
and actions that you visited. And for if
you aggregate kind of all the
trajectories in your data set, you can
train a model to go from the state that
you saw to the sum of rewards that was
observed when you ran the policy. And
you can with this you can kind of form a
supervised learning data set where this
is the label in the data set and you can
train with supervised learning a model
to take as input this and output this
quantity right here and the number of
data points in your data set will be the
number of trajectories times the average
number of time steps. Yeah. Yeah. So the
question is each time your policy
changes do you have to kind of recollect
the data and refit this? Um with this
approach yes uh we we will see
approaches later. This is like the the
simplest and kind of dumbest approach
you can use uh to fit a value function.
Um and we will see approaches where you
can kind of reuse other data. Yeah.
Yeah. So the question was if we're going
to be running a lot of uh kind of
simulations or rollouts of our policy,
is it like unreasonable to try to learn
some estimate of like future states
given the current state in action? Um
the
two things here. If you have a very
simple state space, a very small state
space, um you might be able to uh kind
of store some things and kind of form an
estimate just from storing things. Um
you could also in principle train a
neural network to predict what future
states would be given current states and
actions. Uh there are a set of
approaches that use those uh that do
that and they're called model based
approaches and that they're learning a
model of the world. Uh and we will talk
about those approaches in a few weeks.
Okay. So
this first approach is just to aggregate
kind of run a bunch of samples,
aggregate a data set of our future
rewards. uh and then run supervised
learning to fit an estimated value
function where you can form a kind of a
an L2 error between your predicted value
and the observed sum of rewards and then
minimize that with respect to the
parameters of your value function.
And so what this objective looks like is
minimizing with respect to your
parameters uh the difference between
your
predicted value and
the
uh the example uh or the the sum of
awards that you saw in your data set for
a given I.
And you'll do this for all of the data
points in your uh in your data set. Uh
and so this actually can also be a sum
over i and t uh just for completeness.
So that will be kind of the the
objective and you can run gradient
descent on this objective to fit a value
function on your data point. Do we need
to train a neural network for every
gradient step in this case? So this is
actually different from policy gradient
where we um when we change the gradient
steps here that we take are going to be
trying to fit a value function and uh
the value function isn't changing the
policy and so you can actually take many
gradient steps on this objective uh to
learn a value function uh without having
to recollect your data.
Cool. So this is the simplest approach
for training a value function. Uh it's
called Monte Carlo estimation where
essentially you're just uh yeah running
lots of um simulations running lots of u
of rollouts and then trying to learn how
to predict the outcome of the future
rewards.
Now um there's actually an approach
that's better than this. uh and in
particular
when we think about these sum of rewards
uh maybe it's helpful to draw a picture
in this case. So um
so we have like a bunch of trajectories
that we have sampled
and
um in this case uh what we're doing is
when we have a kind of a state right
here we are summing um the rewards here
as the value.
And
as we're learning this um we're kind of
starting to learn what the value is like
like uh what the value of a given state
is. And this means that
the um like maybe halfway through
training when we're regressing to future
rewards uh we and if we start to get
kind of what is a good value of like
this state right here then we could
actually try to use our own estimate of
this value as the supervision target. Uh
and in particular, if we know that the
reward uh we got a reward at this time
step right here to then get to here,
then we could actually use um that
reward plus our estimate as the
supervision target rather than uh just
using the sum of future reward.
And so um in particular
uh the ideal target is the sum of like
the the true sum of expected rewards. Uh
this is equal to the reward at the
current time step plus the expected
rewards at the next time step.
And
this is uh equal to uh the sum of
rewards at the next time step is equal
to the value of the next state.
And so uh in principle what we could do
is is instead of uh trying to regress to
future rewards, we could regress to the
reward at the current time step plus the
value at the next time step. And so
we're actually going to be um in this
case using our estimate of the value at
the next time step as part of the
supervision target. So um this would be
these are all for a given trajectory and
this would be your new
label for your data set for a given
state.
Yeah. So the question is how often do
you up update these v pies? Uh in
practice you can update them like every
single iteration. uh if it's like really
expensive to update them, you could
update them less frequently like if you
have a really huge neural network. Uh
but in practice, typically we update
them every single uh every single
gradient step. Uh so we have these kind
of bootstrapped estimates. We refer to
this as bootstrapping. So we're actually
kind of bootstrapping off of our own
estimate of the value function as part
of the learning process.
Um we formulate our training data. We're
then going to use the same exact
objective to fit a value function just
regressing to these targets. We just
have different labels in our data set
now. And these labels are changing as we
are changing our as we kind of run
gradient descent on our objective. And
so uh you often will update your labels
every single gradient update. So the
question is is this based on like one
trajectory or is this based on um kind
of multi multiple trajectories where
things are close together. Um so this
data set will be over multiple
trajectories where i is indexing over
trajectories and t is indexing over time
inside those trajectories. The um in
terms of this label uh this will be for
a given data point and it will be um
and it will be uh you're not going to be
running multiple simulations from that
data point. Um, but you're going to be
kind of estimating what would have
happened from your future state rather
than a single sample of what happened in
that trajectory. Uh, and so with this,
you're actually able to get a better
estimate of all of the possible outcomes
that might have happened at the next
state rather than just one outcome. So
you're asking why are we uh why is the
input to the value function just s and
not including previous times?
Oh um so in this expectation um this is
representing so for uh the ideal target
for our um our value function is the sum
of future rewards and you can think
about this sum of future rewards as um
the reward at the current time step uh
which is a deterministic quantity plus
the future rewards um for our uh
conditioned on our current state. Uh and
so this is conditioned on the current
state because uh the the future rewards
is a function of where we are right now.
Um and it's actually only a function of
where we are right now and not anything
else. Yeah. So the question is does this
require that you have like a good
initial value estimate? Um because if
you if it's really bad at the beginning
then um your targets will be really bad.
Um there are some considerations when
initializing it. Although often times
you don't need to do anything like super
fancy to initialize it and you can just
get started training on this directly.
Um you probably don't want to initialize
your neural network such that like the
values are like negative a thousand or
something. Uh like that would be bad. Uh
but usually we don't initialize our
neural networks that way anyway. Um the
if um if I don't know if I've act like
in practice seen any issues with this um
but in principle you could also start
with a Monte Carlo objective just to get
it in the right ballpark and then
continue with um with this update after
that. So is this part of back
propagation and is there a better way to
up than updating the labels every step?
So um the we'll be using back
propagation to optimize that objective
right there. You could also think about
this as like propagating information
backwards in time. Um, which is distinct
from like propagating gradients through
the network. The um, one other name for
this is called temporal difference
learning where we're like looking at the
difference between the the kind of
future time step and the current time
step. The um, but it is like generally
like kind of propagating information
through time is like fairly distinct
from back propagation.
To summarize what we've talked about so
far, Monte Carlo we're supervising with
the roll out sum rewards whereas
bootstrapping we're supervising using
the reward uh plus the current value
estimate of the next state.
Um and if we look at an example uh and
actually yeah
I'll give another kind of exercise for
you to figure out. So let's look at an
example. So we have we've run the policy
maybe we just have two trajectories. In
practice, we'll have more than this. But
say we have two trajectories. One of
these trajectories, the final reward was
negative one. The other trajectory, the
final reward was one.
And along this trajectory, uh before the
final state, the reward is zero.
Um my question for you is um
what estimate would we get for two
different states for the value function?
uh and in particular uh if we were
training uh on the just these two
trajectories and we use Monte Carlo
versus using temporal difference or
bootstrap learning um what would we
estimate the value to be for the blue
state for these two and what would we
estimate the value to be for the pink
state for these two yeah so for Monte
Carlo in the blue state um it's going to
average out the minus1 and the plus one
uh and so this prediction will be zero
Um does anyone want to share another
one?
Yeah. So for the Monte Carlo for this
one, this will be negative one. Uh cuz
it uh will be kind of supervised to
predict the sum of rewards for the
future for this trajectory. Um anyone
want to share
we should wait maybe before we do that
let's let's talk about do you want to do
this one?
>> Sure.
>> Is it a little bit more intuitive to go
this way?
>> Sure.
>> Okay. Yeah. So this will also be zero.
And then does anyone want to do the back
right? Yeah. So for this one it it'll
see this kind of blue one in the future.
This will have a zero and then um this
will also be assigned vot of zero. Um
and so this is an example of where Monte
Carlo and the bootstrapped estimate are
going to be different. And arguably we
get a more accurate estimate from the
kind of bootstrap value because it's
able to uh kind of look at its estimated
the value and actually aggregate
information across trajectories more
effectively.
Um why the Monte Carlo is minus one by
the top right? Yeah. So um the value for
this one is going to be minus one
because the Monte Carlo objective is
supervising to the sum of future rewards
that are observed for each trajectory.
And so for this trajectory which is
black, it only sees um the sum of future
rewards along this trajectory. So it
only sees negative one and anything over
here along this trajectory for Monte
Carlo would have a target of one um
because it only sees the future
trajectories here and it doesn't use uh
it doesn't bootstrap off of its estimate
um that was using all of the
trajectories. Yeah. Yeah. So the Monteol
blue state um it's going to be that
exact state is in the buffer or is in in
your data set for both um for both
trajectories. And so it's going to
average the reward for them. Um but this
is like the only scenario where Monte
Carlo is going to um is going to kind of
get information from both directories
because you have the same exact state in
your data sets with two different
labels.
Why is the bootstrapped blue state zero?
Um, so this is also going to be
averaging the future rewards. It doesn't
have anything necessarily special to
bootstrap off of. Um, and so, uh, kind
of for the same reason that Monte Carlo
is zero, uh, this will also be be zero.
Um, so basically everything after the
blue state, uh, will be have a value
estimate of negative 1 here and
everything after um the the blue state
on the block trajectory is going to have
an estimate of negative one.
Okay, we should move on. Um, so
kind of one question you might ask kind
of looking at this is um there might
also be a middle ground. So Monte Carlo
is going to be have high variance. Um,
but it is completely unbiased whereas
the bootstrapped estimate has much lower
variance. Um, but it actually can be
incorrect because your current estimate
of the value function is going to have
inevitably at least a small amount of
error in it. Um, and so maybe there's a
way um there might be a way to uh
potentially balance this bias and
variance uh a bit more.
And um one way that we can think about
this is if we have our our trajectories
um we can think of the Monte Carlo
version as using the sum of rewards uh
averaged over those trajectories.
Whereas the TD version is going to be
looking at the the first reward plus the
value um right after that. So it's kind
of R plus V for like just like a
temporal difference of just one time
step.
And you can actually sort of like
interpolate between these two estimates
and instead of using just one time step,
you could use n time steps. So you could
look at the reward um for end time
steps, some of the rewards for end time
steps in the future before the variance
has increased substantially and then use
your value estimate after those end time
steps.
Uh and what this would look like is an
equation like this where instead of
summing instead of just using one reward
right here uh and instead of using all
of the sum of rewards, you can sum over
um
you can sum over the the the next uh n
minus one rewards and then use your
value estimate at t plus n. And so this
looks like a sum over from t to t + n
minus one of r of s a plus your
estimated of the value at
um t plus n.
And this would be um in this case it's
going to have less a lot less variance
than the full mon carlo especially if
you have smaller n um and it's going to
be potentially a little bit like less
biased than just using a one-step
temporal difference bootstrap. Uh and so
um you essentially you're going to have
more information about the rewards that
were directly observed.
Uh so this can be written as this and in
this case um this now becomes your
target for supervised learning.
Um and yeah this is often called nstep
returns because you're summing over n
time steps. Um in practice often using
if you set n equals 1 this is uh just
the bootstrap version. If you set n
equals t this is full mon carlo. uh
often times somewhere in between one and
and t works the best in practice. Uh and
this can be especially useful in
scenarios where you have very small time
steps. Uh because if your time step is
like I don't know 10 milliseconds or
something like that then uh very little
uh will have happened in between those
time steps. If you have a very long time
uh trajectory can you use like both of
these? You're asking
Oh yeah, yeah, yeah. Um, you could also
uh like add to your data set like you
could add all of these to your data set
in principle. Um I think that typically
uh like the high variance like labels um
like the things that are like high
variance can deteriorate learning
because it it um yeah it it leads to
more stoasticity and and likewise like
having like if [clears throat] your
values are like not very good then this
can also uh be a challenge and so in
practice you'll usually just pick one of
these versions uh and supervise with
that. um in principle uh you you could
combine them but yeah in practice
usually you don't. Okay,
one aside here. So um so far we've been
summing rewards and we actually talked
in the first lecture um about how in
some cases we might not want to just
blindly sum all rewards in the future.
And in particular, if you think about
scenarios where the length of the
episode is like like infinite like like
or very very long uh then
your estimate of the value can get very
large uh in those cases. Uh and so you
might not want to just be summing over
all of the rewards in the future. Uh and
so a simple trick to handle the fact
that your estimates of the value can get
very big is to
um weight your objective uh weight the
sum of rewards to be biased towards the
earlier rewards.
Uh and the way that you can write this
is um instead of having r plus v, you
can add
a coefficient right here. um where this
if this coefficient is one, it's the
same as before. Um but you can set it to
something like 0.9 or 0.99. And what
this is going to do is it's going to say
that I care more about the rewards at
the current time step and less about the
rewards at the future time steps.
um the
adding this this discount factor that's
discounting future rewards is actually
can be viewed as changing the decision
process slightly. Uh so it's actually
equivalent to saying that
there is kind of some probability that
you will uh that that the agent will
kind of die at any given point in time.
And so this is equivalent to saying that
um with some probability so say like say
gamma is like uh 0.99
um in this case uh using this form is
equivalent to saying that there's a 1%
chance that the agent will enter some
state that has zero reward and and stay
there forever.
Um and so if you have like some original
MDP right here, uh the way that that
this discount factor would change the
MDP is it would say that with some
probability uh with a probability one
minus gamma, you enter this uh this kind
of death state that doesn't uh where you
can't start you can't do anything else
after that. um and the probability of um
the original probabilities in the rest
of the MDP are all multiplied by gamma.
Um the question is is there any
relationship between gamma and like
these endstep things? Um like if gamma
is small would it would that change like
what you do? Um the and yeah the way
that you would modify this objective
would be gamma to the n. Um the
uh possibly I mean I think that the
they're all interconnected in the sense
that the choice of gamma might depend on
the the environment and um and generally
if you're going to be looking further
into the future maybe you're that's
because you're going to be in an
environment that's more deterministic or
has smaller time steps and that would
also affect the the choice of gamma. Um
so the question was uh in terms of
choosing how far you look ahead does
that affect whether you're prioritizing
short versus long-term? Um in this case
the it is more a factor of um so it it
doesn't actually affect uh like how
greedy you are. Um because the value
function is representing the sum of
rewards and so it these are still
estimating the same exact quantity. Um,
it's more a factor of like how far in
the future are you looking ahead in
terms of the rewards and it's more a
factor of like how much how much is the
variance increasing and if the variance
increases kind of somewhat slowly then
you can look further ahead in the
future. Um, if it increases very very
quickly then you might want to use a
smaller n.
Cool. Um, so let's walk through the full
algorithm now. So we talked about
estimating value functions. Uh now let's
actually like put this into practice. So
what we can do is we can sample a batch
of data from our policy.
Then we will fit our value estimate to
the summed rewards in the data. Uh and
we can use um we can do this by looking
at the rewards for a short period of
time and then the value. Um so this
would be the equation for nstep returns.
Uh and then when we fit this, we'll run
multiple gradient steps on this
objective that's trying to minimize the
difference between our estimates and the
observed future rewards.
Um then once we have our estimate of the
value, then we can use that to estimate
the advantage of a particular action by
looking at the reward plus the value at
the next time step minus the value at
the current time step. This is telling
us how um according to our value
function and the reward we saw, how good
is the action that was taken in the data
set.
And then we can use this to get a
gradient for our policy where we will be
increasing the likelihood of actions
that are estimated to be advantageous
and decreasing the likelihood for
actions that are not advantageous.
And then lastly, we'll update our policy
um by applying this gradient step to our
pol to our policy parameters. And then
we can repeat this process to then
sample a new batch of data for our
policy.
Um now note here we have two neural
networks. One is for the policy and one
is for the value function. Um this is
called an actor critic algorithm because
one of the networks is the actor, one of
the networks is the value function which
can also be called a critic because it's
uh criticizing how good a state and
policy is.
Um yeah and and that's our algorithm.
Um and coming coming back to the
examples that we saw before, this is
something that's able to actually make
use of data for example that takes a
step forward and then falls backwards
because you can actually learn um from
the data especially when you use
bootstrapped estimates that taking a
step forward is uh advantageous and has
a positive advantage compared to other
actions that you might take and this is
going to be making much more efficient
use of the data that we've collected.
Cool. Um so review so far we've talked
about policy gradients which is trying
to do more of the good stuff less of the
bad stuff based on what you observe.
Actor critic are learning to estimate
what's good and bad and then doing more
of the good stuff according to your
estimate.
Um and we can get a better estimate um
by using a neural network to try to
explicitly estimate the value function.
Um and then we introduced kind of this
third step where we are fitting this
model as part of the improvement
process.
Um we talked about three different ways
to estimate value. Either directly
looking at summed rewards, um
bootstrapping off the value function and
this hybrid. Um and this is often
referred to as policy evaluation.